{
  "reference_number": "10222",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "I believe that the government should set a target of net zero emissions of heat trapping gases by 2050 in the proposed Zero Carbon\n\n legislation. New Zealand is well positioned to achieve this goal, and setting it will show strong international leadership. With\n knowledge of the impending consequences of runaway climate change, we simply cannot wait for other nations to act. As thoughtful\n and capable people, we need to step forward and show leadership on this issue."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "I believe that the target should be net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050. This may be a difficult goal to meet, but\n including all greenhouse gases will provide equal weighting to various sources and limit the ability of the goal to be “gamed” by\n shifting one emission to another. It also has the potential of setting the standard for other nations."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "I believe that meeting these targets should be done using domestic emissions reductions only, including from new forest planting. If\n\n we use international carbon credits, I believe there is greater opportunity that our achievement in reaching these targets will be\n questioned. We have the capacity to achieve zero carbon though emissions reduction and tree planting in our own economy, without\n outside help."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "I do not recommend that the bill be written so that the target can be changed. We need to set a goal and stick to it. We fail in our\n endeavor for leadership on this issue if we allow ourselves an “escape clause”."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The three budgets allow integration of commercial, technological and social changes, while also giving business and the ETS the\n\n future certainty necessary for forward planning."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": "I believe that each incoming Government should have the option to review the third budget in the sequence. I do not believe that this\nwill unnecessarily weaken the national commitment. In addition, if the nation were to fall behind on its budget, the government should\n\nbe able to change the third target to keep the nation on target."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "From my viewpoint, the most important issue is how to mitigate the effect of the increased cost of emissions across the economy to\nmake sure that no groups are disadvantaged more than others."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": "I believe that it should make the decisions itself, in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS. I believe this function\nshould be outside immediate political control."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "with mandatory reporting requirements."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Thank you for the opportunity to comment on this legislation. As a climate activist (Climate Karanga Marlborough) and retired\ngeoscientist, I think this is very important goal (net zero GHG emissions by 2050) and yet, will be very difficult for our society to\n\naccomplish. I appreciate that citizen consultation is the best way to create a solution that will stick and (hopefully) will be fair to all New\nZealanders."
    }
  ]
}
